《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《罗马公敌》
报告军情
Give report!
斯巴达克斯的骑兵冲破了我军西翼
Spartacus' cavalry has broken our western flank.
该死的野蛮人
That fucking savage.
传令下去  向南边集结列阵
Give signal to re-form to the south.
杀了他
Kill him!
我们得赶紧撤
We must go!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
罗马军队鸣金退兵了
The Romans have sounded retreat.
我们打赢了
We have won the day.
我们啥也没赢
We have won nothing.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯又从我们手心里溜了
Cossinius and Furius again slip from grasp.
不过他们那么多走狗没能溜掉
The same cannot be said for many that stood with them.
漫山遍野都是尸体
The field is thick with the dead.
活该如此  这些家伙还妄想再次奴役我们
Deserved fate for all who would see us again to shackle and whip.
又战败了
Another standard lost?
真是大伤共和国的元气  科西尼斯
It is a grave wound inflicted upon the Republic, Cossinius.
如果我们没有及时撤出来
A deeper one would have been suffered,
损失就更惨重了
had we not withdrawn from battle.
真他妈的没道理
It confounds the fucking senses.
这帮乌合之众怎么一而再地挫败我们呢
How could a handful of errant slaves continue to vex us?
恐怕元老院严重低估了他们的兵力
I fear their numbers have been sorely underestimated within the Senate.
斯巴达克斯的人马
Spartacus' mongrel horde
自从在维苏威击败葛雷博后
has swelled with each passing victory,
每次获胜都有壮大
since Glaber's defeat at Vesuvius.
他们攻占卢卡尼亚矿区后  增加了数千人
They added thousands to rank liberating the mines of Lucania.
全国各地的奴隶
Slaves across the Republic,
多年安守本分  侍奉主人
humble and grateful to their masters
如今见斯巴达克斯风生水起
for so many years, have broken to treachery
竟然也纷纷变节倒戈
in the wake of ever expanding legend of Spartacus.
斯寇法在凯洛河岸战败后
Untold numbers joined his cause
不知道有多少人投奔了叛军
after Scrofa fell to him on the banks of the Calor.
他的鹰旗和束棒落入叛军之手
His standards and fasces falling to the enemy,
其人也未能脱身
as the man himself.
区区一个该死的奴隶竟然能翻江倒海
Such chaos and death at the hands of a fucking slave.
如果再不派出援军
You will discover this fucking slave
你就会发现这个该死的奴隶
at the very gates of Rome itself,
要一路杀到罗马城下了
if reinforcements are not dispatched.
卢库勒斯在黑海附近与米特拉达梯人作战
Lucullus battles Mithridates near the Black Sea.
安东尼乌斯出海进剿克里特岛的海盗
Antonius sails against the pirates plaguing Crete.
庞培还在跟西班牙的塞多留叛军苦战
Pompey yet struggles with the renegade Sertorius in Espainia.
如此乱局  元老院已经力不从心了
The resources of the Senate are drained by these conflicts.
我们既没有兵力  也没有支付军饷的财力
We have not the men nor the coin to procure them.
有一个人可以自掏腰包支援前线
There is one among us who could fund endeavor from his own purse.
对他来说不过九牛一毛
And never feel sting of its cost.
我并不希望那人搅和进来
I had hoped to avoid involving the man.
我们也不愿意欠他的人情  梅泰勒斯
We would not be beholden to him any more than you, Metellus.
要是还有出路  我们绝对不找他
Produce alternative, and we shall seize upon it.
很好
Very well.
我这就回罗马请求克拉苏
I shall return to Rome and entreat Crassus
协助我们剿灭斯巴达克斯叛军
to aid in crushing Spartacus and his rebellion.
与此同时  抚平我们的伤痛
And in the act, attempt to redress grievous injury
重拾共和国的光荣
inflicted upon the honor of the Republic.
战场上丢弃的武器和马匹都到手了
The field has been stripped of weapons and horses.
罗马军队的损失又充实了我们的力量
The Romans' loss again becomes our bounty.
甘尼克斯呢
What of Gannicus?
我想听听他的报告
I would have his report as well.
你也知道他
You well know the man.
打了胜仗就去找乐子
He favors celebration after a victory.
经常是几天几夜
Often for many days.
等灭了科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯
A thing I would gladly give blessing
我倒是非常支持他找乐子
after Cossinius and Furius fall from concern.
看来他们不是傻子
They have proven themselves no fools.
还是有可能采取大胆行动
And may yet attempt bold maneuver.
在附近山岭上加派巡逻队
Double our sentries in surrounding hills.
不能被他们打个措手不及
I would not be caught unaware.
你也太高估那些混蛋了
You give those shits credit beyond due.
罗马人才会轻视对手  艾力冈
Underestimating your opponent is a Roman trait, Agron.
你可别受影响了
Do not fall prey to it.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯气数已尽
Cossinius and Furius come to the end of their days.
每天都有几百个奴隶
With each passing sun, hundreds of slaves
投身于我们的大业
break bond to join our cause.
艾力冈说得对
Agron is not wrong in this.
很快我们就有人数优势了
Soon we shall have the advantage of numbers.
验验他们的本事  武装起来
Gauge prowess of all that have joined us, and see them readied.
我要尽快找机会出击
I would strike again at nearest opportunity,
罗马的那帮蠢货妄想一脚踩死我们
and give further warning to the fools in Rome
就让他们尝尝厉害
seeking to grind us beneath heel.
几个月了  他每天都跟那人缠斗
Every day for months he wrestles with the man,
哼哼哈嘿不绝于耳
groans and grunts filling ear.
您父亲学得很用心
Your father is a dedicated student.
还非要我站在一边瞧着
And I forced to stand witness to the lessons,
更要紧的大事都没人顾了
while more pressing matters fall to ill attention.
对不起  主人
Apologies, Dominus.
我打得兴起  没有留神
I lose myself in the heat of contest.
划伤而已
Less than a scratch.
刚才毫无防备  这伤算是太轻了
Worse deserved for not anticipating blow.
您学得很快
You are quick of study.
但当您借势猛攻时  侧面便空门大开
Yet you open flank to injury when perceived advantage is pressed.
元老院的很多人都是这么完蛋的
The ruin of many a man within the Senate.
等吃过晚饭再来练习吧
Let us return to lesson after evening meal is broken.
告退  主人
Dominus.
看来传言是真的  克拉苏
The rumors prove true, Crassus.
你竟然接受奴隶的教导
You take instruction from a slave.
海拉努斯在竞技场稳坐冠军宝座多年
Hilarus stood a champion of the arena for many years.
我为他花的钱之多  你这辈子都没见过
I paid his lanista more coin than you'll ever see in your life
不只是买他
to purchase the man,
还有他的角斗经验
and impart what he's learned of the games.
了解那些血溅沙场的人
And of the men who have drawn blood upon the sands.
角斗士
Gladiators.
这正是我来的目的
You strike upon very subject of my visit.
我们能不能私下谈谈
If we may break word in private?
我向来以成年人的要求培养提比略
Oh, Tiberius is well trained in the ways of men.
也希望他多接触元老院的事务
I would expose him to those of the Senate as well.
是这样  我们在镇压斯巴达克斯叛军时
To the matter, we've have suffered unexpected complications
遇到了意料之外的复杂情况
in our conflict with the rebel Spartacus.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯完蛋了
Cossinius and Furius have fallen?
他们逃过一死  但急需援军
They live, but find themselves inneed of reinforcement.
正当多事之秋  这要求实在很难满足
An expensive thing to acquire, in these troubled times.
他们肯定被斯巴达克斯干到菊花都残了
Their asses must be sore from the ramming Spartacus has given,
不惜来求我
to come begging to me.
不是求你
No one is begging.
他们是在向元老院的成员要求援助
They are asking assistance from a loyal member of the Senate.
援助多少
How much assistance?
一万人
Ten thousand men.
要养这么庞大的军队
It would take considerable coin and effort
财力精力可不少
to raise such a force.
作为回报  你可以有指挥权
And in return you will be offered a command.
位次当然在科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯之后
Under Cossinius and Furius, of course.
这话最好由他们亲口说出来
An offer better received from the men themselves.
他们撤到了努凯里亚郊区的一座宅子里
They've withdrawn to a villa on the outskirts of Nuceria,
在他们军团北边不远的地方
within short ride of what remains of their legion to the north.
斯巴达克斯仍在坎帕尼亚山区积聚力量
Spartacus continues to gather force in the valley of Campania.
你知道  不到万不得已  我是不会来的
You know I would not have come if situation did not demand of it.
没错  我很清楚
No. You would not.
我同意他们的条件
Their terms are agreeable.
我立刻把消息传达给他们
I will dispatch message to them immediately.
还是我派人去吧
Best I send my own men,
确保这条消息送到该送的地方
to ensure it arrives at intended destination.
悉听尊便
Whatever your will.
说实话  我原以为你最起码
To voice truth of it, I had expected you to extort
要借机索要虚名高位
inflated title at the very least,
就像庞培领军讨伐塞多留时一样
as Pompey did to take his charge against Sertorius.
我只关心挣来的名位
My interest lies only in title and honor earned.
抱歉  是我小人之见了
Apologies for ever suspecting any less.
您居然同意屈居科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯之下
You would agree to serve beneath Cossinius and Furius,
手无实权
absent true command?
看来是的
It would appear so.
我以前听您痛骂那两人
I have heard how you berate their names,
认为他们和梅泰勒斯元老根本是愚蠢无能
how foolish and vain you think them and Senator Metellus.
- 父亲  - 现在不是说人闲话的时候
- Father... - The time for words has ended.
斯巴达克斯必须死
Spartacus must fall,
而我要选择正确的道路  尽快实现这一目的
and I shall set upon what path I must to see day hastened.
为了罗马的荣耀
For the glory of Rome.
当时可亮瞎了我的狗眼
I saw it with my own fucking eyes!
战到酣处  鲜血和脑浆堆到膝盖这里
In the heat of battle, blood and brains thick to the knee.
而甘尼克斯  就挺立其中
and Gannicus, in the middle of it all!
掏出他的巨鸟
Strips to his fucking cock,
朝罗马人狂吼  要他们跪在面前
bellowing to the Romans to kneel before him
接受他的琼浆玉液
and receive golden tribute!
我要解释  我那天酒喝了太多
In my defense, I had taken much wine that day,
没想到斯巴达克斯转而进攻斯寇法
not expecting Spartacus to turn and attack Scrofa.
还有酒吗
There is more wine?
我的朋友都饥渴难耐了
My friends, are of thirst.
你女人带礼物来了
Your woman brings gifts!
礼物  是的
Gifts, yes.
但不是给你的
Not for you.
出去
Out.
这是我的帐篷
It is my fucking tent.
出去
Out.
我们再找个帐篷  但愿也有一屋子妞儿
We shall find another. Hopefully as well stocked.
斯巴达克斯要见你
Spartacus need to see you.
那就先让他等等吧
Then let him see me a while longer.
是错觉吗
Is it imagining,
还是因为打了仗我们就爽翻天了
or do we rise to heights unknown in wake of battle?
谁不是呢
As all men do,
打赢了杀爽了兴致就高了
when bathed in blood and victory.
那要是罗马灭亡  我们非爽到天崩地裂不可
When Rome falls, I fear we shall split the heavens in celebration.
等朱庇特掉下来
And fuck Jupiter
老子不操翻他才怪
as he plummets to the earth.
怎么  你自以为像神一样威猛
Oh, you believe you fuck as a God now?
我可不是说大话
I boast but upon evidence given.
豪言壮语加美酒
Couple proud words with wine,
再好好兑现你的话
and see them better received.
你今天在战场表现很不错
You afforded yourself well upon the field this day.
你很惊讶吗
You stand surprised?
我一直都相信你  纳西尔
I have always believed in you, Nasir.
即便在你还是叛逆的叙利亚小男奴的时候
Even when you were yet a contrary little Syrian slave boy.
我的双眼被蒙蔽了
My eyes were yet shrouded.
是斯巴达克斯让我睁眼  我永远欠他一份情
I am forever in Spartacus' debt, for parting veil.
我们所有人都欠他
A debt shared equally by all.
我们要用罗马人的命来偿还
One we shall repay with Roman lives.
你召见我吗
You summoned me?
本来没有必要
I would not have had to.
可你没跟克雷斯还有艾力冈一起来汇报
If you had reported in with Crixus and Agron days ago.
我当时有更要紧的事
My attentions were called by pressing matters.
女人和美酒吗
Of women and drink?
还能有别的吗
Are there any more so?
你不来汇报  这事情就不算完
Days can not pass after battle without your report.
我们打了仗
We fought.
打赢了
We won.
我这么说够了吗
Does that cover needed ground?
你对付罗马军队的本事我们都看到了
You have proven valuable asset against the Romans.
但我希望你不光是一介武夫
Yet I would have you stand more than just another sword.
还要站到克雷斯和我身边  成为领袖
Take rightful place beside Crixus and myself, as a leader.
为了奥诺玛默斯  我甘愿为你而死
I will give life to your cause, in honor of Oenomaus.
我甚至相信有一天真的会为你而死
I may even believe in it myself upon a day.
但我不是领袖  也不想当领袖
But I am no leader, nor seek to be one.
但很多人已经视你为领袖
There are many that already look to you as such.
无数人会追随你去战斗
A greater number still would follow you in battle.
你是说为我而死吗
You mean die for me?
为我们的大业
For the cause.
我可不想在弟兄们面前高高在上
I would not be set above my brothers,
以为我多么厉害
and thought greater than I am.
很多人都是这样看待你的
As many begin to think of you.
我并不希望这样
I do not wish it.
但却是事实
Yet it is so.
他们把你当成神了
They begin to speak of you as a god.
要是你拿自己当凡人  估计他们不乐意
And may react poorly when you prove yourself mortal.
我只关心如何打败罗马人
Victory against the Romans is my only concern.
怎样才算打败他们呢
And how is it defined?
杀了科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯之后吗
When Cossinius and Furius struck from this world?
你知道那远远没有结束
You know that will not be the end of it.
罗马肯定紧接着派出更多人
Rome will send more and more in their wake.
来者必死
Then they too shall fall.
等我们推翻了强大的共和国之后呢
And when we have laid waste to the mighty Republic?
你又要向何处宣泄怒火呢
What will you turn your wrath upon then hmmm?
逼你走上这条路的人
The men that set you on this path,
夺走你妻子的人
the men that took your wife from you.
连同他们的妻子都已经不在世上
They are gone from this world. Their wives too.
露迪雅和伊莉西娅的死讯都传来了
In past news of Lucretia and Ilithyia's fall.
多少人命都无法偿还苏拉的血债
A thousand lives would not equal Sura's.
我也爱过一个女人
I dared to love a woman once.
当我还是巴蒂塔斯的奴隶时
When I was a slave to Batiatus.
她还在世吗
She yet draws breath?
只要她能活过来  我愿放弃一切
I would give the world to have it so.
我们这样的人  都是同病相怜
A fate too common, for men such as us.
我已经为她报了仇  就像你一样
I had my vengeance, as you did.
却不能弥补心中的失落
And stood as empty.
直到奥诺玛默斯原谅了我的背叛
Until Oenomaus forgave betrayal.
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus?
我爱上的人是他的妻子
It was his wife I lost heart to.
虽然我已获得了自由
Even when freedom was gained,
我心中的枷锁却无法解开
shackles of what I had done to those I loved remained.
奥诺玛默斯临死前帮我解开了这枷锁
With final breath, Oenomaus struck chains that bound me.
我却早已没有贴心的人
There is no one I hold to heart left
倾吐安慰的话
to break such balming words.
既然没有  就只能说给自己听了
Absent such, a man must speak them to himself.
说了也没有用
Words also denied me.
所以你在千军万马  浴血奋战中寻求慰藉
You seek them in the voice of thousands, clamoring for blood?
我救不回我的妻子
I could not save my wife.
我要战斗到有那么一天
And I can fight to see a day
没有无辜的生命受到漠视
when no innocent life is so easily disregarded.
罗马及其残酷的统治成为遥远的历史
A day when the Romans and their cruelty are but distant memory.
但愿那一天  你能找到安宁  兄弟
May you find peace in its arrival, brother.
让我们尽情享受女人和美酒
Let us share wine and women,
不要再讨论这种沉重的话题了
and set aside such heavy fucking thoughts.
你的心意我领了
The offer is much appreciated.
那我便以你的名义饮酒作乐
Then I will drink and fuck in your name.
你振臂一呼  我浴血奋战
Fight when called upon.
在你这疯子的指引下
The very steps to the Roman Senate
一直杀到罗马元老院
if that is where your madness leads.
加价到三百五十第纳尔
Raise offer to 350 Denarii
外加两尤格（约两英亩）土地
and two iugera of land.
我们必须尽快招募足够的兵力
We must elevate numbers quickly.
我交给萨比努斯去办  确保完成
I will dispatch Sabinus and see it done.
我以为你已经上床睡了
I thought you to bed.
提比略总跟他讲打仗的事
Tiberius has filled his ears with talk of war.
他脑袋里只有打仗  哪儿睡得着觉
The battle rages in his head, vanquishing slumber.
是真的吗
Is it true?
您要带兵去打斯巴达克斯
You ride with an army against Spartacus?
当然  为了保卫共和国
Yes to defend the Republic,
捍卫罗马  匹夫有责
as is the duty of all Romans.
我也是罗马人  我跟您去
I'm a Roman. I will go with you.
等你长大成人
Oh, would that you were of an age,
就能和父亲并肩作战了
to stand by your father's side.
现在该睡觉了  普布利乌斯
Now for your bed, Publius,
去梦见你将来的荣耀
and dream of future laurels.
是  父亲
Yes, father.
只要你一声令下
He would follow you to the shores
他是刀山火海都愿追随你
of the afterlife, if so commanded.
提比略也一样
As would Tiberius.
我的军队出征时  他自然有一席之地
He will hold place amongst my troops when they march.
一席之地
A place?
身居高位才对  要配得上他的名头
He deserves position of note, worthy of the name he bears.
要做护民官  他的资历还不够
He does not yet hold the years for the title of Tribune.
花点钱  再游说游说  就不用管这些规定
Coin and persuasion would see such rules set aside--
他还不够格
He has not earned it.
提比略有冲锋陷阵的能力
Tiberius has shown great promise as a soldier.
但他缺乏谋略和洞察力
Yet he falls from target in strategy and discerning mind.
那就好好指点他
Then lend instruction.
我一直在教导他
My lessons never cease.
但修行靠个人
It is for him to apply them.
公务要处理到深夜吗
Your work carries into night?
要通宵达旦
And threatens break of dawn.
我命人给你准备食物和酒
I shall see food and wine brought.
克芮会满足我的需要
Kore shall tend to my needs.
好吧
Of course.
我在床上等你
Your bed awaits.
需要的话就过来
If you find want of it.
凭他的荣誉早该手握实权了
It is an honor long deserved, to be given command.
结果还是屈居科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯之下
One he finds beneath Cossinius and Furius.
我还从没见过你父亲
I have never known your father
愿意屈居在别人的手下呢
to remain beneath anyone for length of time.
也许是年岁大了  他对荣誉和人民的拥戴
Ah, perhaps the years have tempered desire for laurels
没那么强烈渴望了
and adulation of the crowds.
你的渴望呢
And what of your desires?
足以把阿波罗烧死
Apollo himself would be set ablaze by them.
那我可记着别太靠近你
I shall remember not to stand too near,
怕翅膀融化了
for fear of melted wings.
我要你跟我在一起  萨比努斯
I would not have you from my side in this, Sabinus.
诸神也无法把我拉开
The gods themselves could not wrest me from it.
我负责提高价码  招兵买马
I will see offer raised and numbers elevated.
谢谢
Gratitude.
我想起了你和萨比努斯小时候
I recall a time when you and Sabinus were but children,
用木棍打仗玩的情形
playing at war with wooden sticks.
那是以前玩的游戏了
Such games are of the past.
对你父亲而言足以说明问题
A thing yet proven to your father.
别让他有理由继续质疑你的能力
Do not give him cause to further doubt you.
当我上战场屠杀敌人时
Any shall be swept from thought,
一切怀疑都会烟消云散
when I stand awash in the blood of our enemies.
注意左边
Watch your left!
当心中招
Watch for the swing!
你他妈的注意防守啊
Raise fucking guard!
这小子一天比一天厉害了
Your boy grows fiercer by the day.
很快我就不敢叫他小家伙了
Soon even I shall fear to call him little man.
你现在要是跪地求饶
At least now I will be able to understand you
我完全能理解  傻逼
when you yield, you simple shit.
斯巴达克斯
Spartucus.
下一个  准备好
Next man! Take position!
快开始  快开始
Let's go! Let's go!
- 开始  - 上啊
- Begin! - Come on!
我们在掂量新来的人能耐如何
We test the last of those that have joined us.
你觉得怎么样
How do you find them?
很有激情
Enthusiastic.
不过技术太糙
Yet short of skill.
我们当中很多人以前也是这样
Many among us once stood as such.
他们很快就能证明自己的价值
These will soon prove as worthy.
恐怕有人不行
Perhaps not all.
下一个
Next man!
不要多话
Do not speak of this.
快走
Go.
你是迪欧特莫斯
Diotimos?
是又怎样
If I were?
进去
Inside.
快点
Quickly.
我只能分这么多了  少他妈的问这问那
I can spare no more than this, so do not fucking ask.
谢谢  谢谢
Gratitude, gratitude.
你宰了一匹马
You have killed a horse?
你他妈的小点声
Lower fucking voice.
让人知道这里有肉的话  我就搞不到畜生了
I would not follow the animal in crush news of meat would bring.
谁允许你这么做的
Who gave permission?
战场上骑兵的价值可是步兵的十倍
A man atop a horse in battle is valued ten upon foot.
它在与罗马人的交战中受了很重的伤
He was gravely wounded against the Romans.
我倒是想找山上那位大人批准一下
I would have sought permission from the great man upon the hill,
但斯巴达克斯国王正忙着四处征战
but King Spartacus is far too busy waging war
哪有闲心管这种鸡毛蒜皮的破事
to bother with such low concerns.
你怎会有这样的想法
What moves you to such thoughts?
睁开狗眼一看你不就知道了
Open fucking eyes you have your answer.
我有点后悔当初离开温柔的海风
I begin to question turning from the calm of the ocean breeze
城墙的庇护了
and the safety of my city's walls.
这么说你以前是自由人
You were a free man, then?
早就不是了
Far removed.
我在希留爱沙山为一个混账东西
I toiled beneath the heel of a most unpleasant shit
累死累活地工作
in Sinuessa en Valle.
但他娘的最起码能管吃管穿
Yet he at least provided for fucking needs.
你认为自由是毫无代价的吗
Did you expect freedom to come absent cost?
不
No.
但他妈的既然不管吃不管穿
Yet absent fucking plan to be clothed or fed
我们只能自力更生
we must take matters into our own hands.
要是等那位携雨之使者携他娘的大雨来
Or risk early grave waiting for the Bringer of Fucking Rain
我们怕是早饿死了
to bless us with much needed shower.
这天很快便转冷了
Weather will soon turn cold.
- 我们就...  - 斯巴达克斯
- And with it... - Spartacus!
一群罗马兵从北面过来了
A clutch of Romans ride from the north,
打算通过我们控制的地方
attempting to slip past our position.
你就是斯巴达克斯
You are Spartacus?
- 万分抱歉  我不...  - 不用说了
- Apologies, I did... - Still tongue.
你也许不能每天都吃饱穿暖
You may not always have full belly or warm cloak,
但只要我还活着  你说什么都是自由的
but while I draw breath you have freedom to speak your heart.
即便是说山上那位大人的坏话
Even against the great man upon the hill.
我的妈呀
Fuck the gods.
站住
You there!
你离叛军营地这么近  有何企图
What is your purpose so near rebel encampment?
同你一道的还有谁
Who else is with you?
回答我
Find fucking tongue.
有谁和你一起
Who is with you?
死亡
Death.
我们要追上他
We must follow.
不用  矛给我  快
No. A spear. Quickly.
我的剑术与你不相上下
I stand your equal with sword.
可你他妈的掷得一手好矛
Yet you have me by fucking spear.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
这个人身上有信
This one carried a message.
上面怎么说
What does it say?
一万人
Ten thousand?
由马科斯·克拉苏亲自率领
Led by Marcus Crassus Himself.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯将获得强援
Cossinius and Furius will see their numbers swell,
占据绝对优势
stripping advantage.
我们可以设下埋伏
We could lay trap.
这里  亚壁古道的路上
Here, upon the Appian Way.
在他们跟弟兄会师之前  杀他们个措手不及
Catch them by surprise before they have chance to join their brothers.
这样一来我们就会陷入北面进军的克拉苏
That would place us between Crassus advancing from the north
与南面科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯的包夹当中
and Cossinius and Furius in the south.
我们的人可应付不了腹背受敌
We do not have the men to face armies on both fronts.
天平偏向他们之前  我们必须
We must strike Cossinius and Furius
主动攻击科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯
before odds tip to imbalance.
我们打得他们叫苦不迭
We have inflicted nagging wound.
可几个月来都没能浇灭他们的士气
Yet for months we have failed to shatter resolve of their men.
用他们将军的脑袋开路
Perhaps the heads of their commanders
也许就能动摇他们了
carried before us would so sway them.
取上将之首可不是探囊取物啊
Trophies proven difficult to win.
于百万军中  的确如此
On the field of battle, yes.
但据纸上所写  这信并非要送进
By what is written here, message was not directed
大军之中
to where their troops lie.
这上面说  望此消息能安全抵达宅邸
It speaks of hope that word finds them safe within the villa.
他们躲起来了
They have gone to ground?
有热水澡  还有女人的身子
Warm bath and the comfort of women,
我到罗马可没白去
if my days in Rome are of worth.
这宅子在哪儿
Where is this villa?
并未写明
It does not say.
那还不是毫无进展
Then we return to beginning.
我们在此截杀的克拉苏信使正往东南方向去
We intercepted Crassus' men here, riding southeast.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯肯定不会
Cossinius and Furius would seek to stay
与大军相隔过远
within reasonable distance of their men.
他们的宅子肯定在这个地区
Would place their villa somewhere within this region.
怎么找出来呢
How do we divine which is theirs?
如你所说  他们不是傻子
They are no fools, as you have said.
只要观察哨岗的分布就能看出来
We will know location by placement of sentries.
他们肯定也会在宅子附近
And sizable force they no doubt have
部署相当的兵力加以保护
without villa to lend protection.
那我们就倾巢而出  发动奇袭
Then we descend upon them with every sword we have.
不
No.
大军进攻宅子很容易打草惊蛇
We risk discovery moving against the villa with large numbers.
科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯受了惊吓
Cossinius and Furius would be alerted,
便有可能再次从我们手中溜走
and have chance to slip again from grasp.
少数几个人却可以神不知鬼不觉地渗透进去
Yet a few men might penetrate defense unnoticed...
以少敌多
A few against many.
历历往事啊
Much as the old days.
甘尼克斯  克雷斯  跟我来
Gannicus, Crixus... I would have you at my side.
那我就无所事事  袖手旁观吗
I am to stand idle, with arm up fucking ass?
我不在的时候由你领兵
You are to lead in my absence.
集结所有能使兵器的男女
Gather every man and woman that can hold weapon.
然后呢
Towards what purpose?
做一件决定我们成败的大事
One of vital importance, if we are to gain victory.
发了疯才会定这样的计划
It is plan born of fevered mind.
他的计划一向如此
As often springs from his brow.
- 但如果我们...  - 如果
- Yet if we can see it... - If.
一听到这词  天都黑了
A word forever casting shadow.
你的光芒足以照亮最黑暗的夜晚
You burn brightly enough to light darkest night.
我在担心你  你还来奉承我
I voice concern and you offer flattery.
我说的是实话
I offer truth.
你的光芒比得过太阳
Your fire blazes to rival the fucking sun.
这双手  曾因不堪回首的记忆颤抖
These hands, once trembled with broken memory,
如今却如钢铁般强硬有力
now stand as strong as the steel they wield.
多亏了你
Because of you.
多亏你坚强的心
Because your heart is strong.
还有你摧不垮的意志
And your will undeniable force,
我经常能看到这一点
as I have often discovered.
我不要离开你
I would not be from your side.
我也不离开你
Nor I yours,
但今晚必须如此
but this night it must be so.
好好跟着艾力冈
Stay near to Agron,
听他的命令
and follow command.
多杀几个罗马人
Kill many Romans.
带着他们
And return to my arms
滚烫的鲜血
with their blood
回到我怀抱
hot upon you.
让尸山血海
The bodies of the dead
来迎接克拉苏和他的军队
be all that greet Crassus and his army.
拿剑来
Sword.
要想进攻斯巴达克斯
There is yet much to be done,
我们还有很多事情要做
if we are to move against Spartacus.
嗯  很多
Hmmm, much.
那您还浪费时间跟低贱的奴隶对打
Yet you waste hour sparring with a common slave.
以前别人也是这么看斯巴达克斯的吧
Was Spartacus not also once thought of as such?
你也不把他放在心上吗
Would you dismiss him so casually as well?
没有  不过斯巴达克斯打胜了仗也只是奴隶
No. Yet for all his victories spartacus is still a slave.
他是条汉子  跟有名有位的人没区别
He's a man. No better or worse than any sharing title.
您拿他跟罗马公民相提并论吗
You would place him upon equal footing with a Roman?
从某种角度来说  他站的位置更高
In some regards, he's proven to stand even higher.
你真的以为  有了财富和地位
You believe wealth and position grant you
就能高人一等吗
advantage over those beneath you?
我相信  任何方面我们都凌驾于奴隶之上
I believe we tower above a slave in all things,
无论这奴隶姓甚名谁
no matter what name he bears.
言出必行  证明你所说的话
Then couple words with actions, and prove belief.
你受到过良好的罗马战技训练
Well, you've been well trained in the Roman ways of combat.
打败一个低贱的奴隶不成问题
Surely you can best a common slave.
主人  非常抱歉  我不是故意的...
Apologies, Dominus. I did not mean to...
你不过是给他上了必要的一课
You did but teach lesson sorely needed,
正如斯巴达克斯教训那些自以为神
as Spartacus schools those who consider themselves gods,
不可一世的家伙
perched far above lesser men,
笑话他们从天上栽到地下
And laughs as they tumble from the heavens.
他们人太多了
There are too many.
我们无法应付
Even for us.
那就先等等看
Then let us pause moment.
等他们的兵力分散
And see numbers thinned.
骰子已经掷出  后悔也来不及
The die has been cast. We cannot reverse throw.
梅泰勒斯那边还没有消息
There has been no word from Metellus.
他耽搁了太久
He takes overly long.
我们又怎能指望朗吉努斯那边尽快答复呢
And with what haste could we expect reply from Longinus for aid?
山南高卢比罗马远一倍
Cisalpine Gaul lays twice distance than Rome.
不然送信过去
At least consider dispatching message--
民政官
Praetor.
叛军正在我军北面附近集结
The rebel army gathers near our legions in the north.
命令莫姆缪斯率一军二军前去支援
Give Mummius orders for first and second cohorts to move to support them.
去他娘的克拉苏
To fuck with Crassus.
我们集合军队  自己拿下斯巴达克斯
We shall rejoin our men and take Spartacus ourselves.
快取盔甲和剑来
Fetch armor and sword! Quickly!
艾力冈率军到北边  引开了他们的兵力
Agron's advance on position to the north draws them away.
还有守军
Not all.
诸神肯定听到了我的祈祷
The gods have heard my prayers.
兵不血刃怎么好吹牛呢
There is no boast in easy victory.
注意隐蔽
Stay to the shadows.
速战速决
And let us end this.
他说话的语气还当我是小孩
He speaks to me as he would a child.
那就别撅嘴耍脾气  用行动证明
Then prove him wrong, and do not pout as one.
军队还没有组建好
An army not yet raised to maturity.
他既不筹备远征  也不关心作战计划
Preparation for long march and campaign ignored.
整天就跟这头畜生打来打去
All in favor of playing with this fucking brute.
他到底在想什么
I do not understand his mind.
受伤的自尊心先放一边  换位思考
Set aside wounded pride and think as he would.
一切必能水落石出
And see shrouded mystery parted.
加快速度  不要引起他们的注意
Swiftly. Before they are discovered from their post.
不知道里面有多少人
We do not know how many await inside.
但愿人不要太少
Let us pray they are not too few.
你们都是疯子
I am encircled by mad fucks.
我也快疯了
And begin to count myself as one.
诸神保佑
The gods favor us.
斯巴达克斯不信神
Spartacus holds no belief in them.
希望今晚诸神证明我错了
I pray this night they prove me wrong.
主人  掌握技巧需要时间
Dominus, it takes time to master technique.
这当然容易使人沮丧
I well know it can swell frustration.
我不是因为自己无能而沮丧
My frustrations lie not with myself.
主人  如果我做了什么冒犯到您
Dominus? If I have done something to offend...
是你没做什么冒犯到了我
The only offense lies in what you do not do.
你进攻时保留了实力
You hold back in your assault.
你觉得我不配和你较量吗
Do you think I'm not worthy of it?
正如元老院认为我不配当统帅
As the Senate believes me unworthy of a true command?
不是的  主人
No, Dominus.
您是最值得尊敬的人
None stand more worthy of respect than you.
那就表现给我看
Then see it given.
向我进攻
Come at me.
就像你在竞技场上与对手搏杀
As you would an opponent in the arena,
毫不留情
absent thought of mercy.
父亲
Father--
我们都有要学的东西
We all have lessons that must learned.
我视其为终极考验
I would have this my final test.
只有过了这一关  我才算做好准备
And in its completion, knowledge that I am readied
面对那些与你经受过同样训练的人
to face those trained in your arts upon field of battle.
您是要我杀了您
You ask me to kill you.
我是命令你放胆一试
I command you to try.
那您就是置我于死地了
Then you command my death.
如果您获胜  便意味着我丢掉了性命
If you're victorious, it will be at the cost of my life.
如果您倒在我的剑下  我依旧难逃一死
If you fall to my sword, my life is equally forfeit.
提比略  你来作证
Tiberius. Bear witness.
如果海拉努斯击倒我
If Hilarus strikes me down
那便赏赐他自由之身
he's to be rewarded with his freedom
以及一万第纳尔
and ten thousand denarii.
您没开玩笑吧
You cannot be serious.
最大的敌人莫过于疑虑
A man's true enemy is doubt.
我不能带着疑虑与斯巴达克斯交战
A thing I would not carry into battle against Spartacus.
做出选择吧
Make choice.
否则就是一死
Or fall where you stand.
遵命  主人
Your will, Dominus.
任您吩咐
My hands.
一队和二队快马加鞭与军团会合
First and second garrison ride to join the legion.
斯巴达克斯的兵力不足以一击制胜
Spartacus does not hold the numbers for decisive victory.
他莽撞进军是何意图
What is his mind in such attack?
那我们就敲开他的脑壳
Let us see his skull split open,
看看他到底想了些什么
and read his fucking thoughts upon the ground--
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
后退
Fall back.
靠拢
Stay together.
您快阻止他们
You must stop this.
他下了命令
He has given command.
我必须服从
It must be obeyed.
来啊
Come on!
我们必须送您到安全的地方
We must see you to safety.
我他妈的再也不要从他面前逃跑了
I will not fucking turn from him again.
请您冷静  等我们召集人马回来
Seize reason. We will return with more men
势必拿下斯巴达克斯
and see Spartacus to his fate.
别让他们逃了
Don't let them away!
上啊
Go!
您在等待时机
You were waiting...
让我误以为您犯了我先前提醒过的错误
for me to think you'd made misstep I warned you of...
知识与耐心
Knowledge and patience.
是击败强者的唯一方法
The only counter to greater skill.
您学得很好
You have been well schooled.
你的教导
Know that your service
我永远铭记于心
will not pass unremembered.
我答应要奖给你的赏金
The coin I promised had you bested me
将用来建造纪念碑
shall be set towards monument
以缅怀传奇角斗士海拉努斯
to the storied gladiator Hilarus.
主人  能为您效力是我无上的荣耀
It has been the greatest of honors to have served you, Dominus.
这是我的荣耀
The honor was mine.
该死的野蛮人  封死了出口
Fucking savages have blocked us from egress.
先躲在这里吧
Take shelter here.
我才不要当猎人陷阱里的困兽
I will not fall trapped as fucking animal.
你们败了
Your cause is lost.
是我失误
The mistake is mine.
没料到你们竟然趁夜偷袭
In not foreseeing you would attack in the night,
干出盗贼刺客那样无耻的勾当
as the thieves and cutthroats you prove.
下次别犯同样的错
A mistake you shall not make again.
说出受降的条件  我们了结这一切
Name terms of surrender, and let us be done with this.
罗马人的信誉于我一文不值
There are none I would trust a Roman to honor.
带走他们的首级
Gather their heads.
形势急转而下
A most ill-fated turn.
他们死就死了  可不幸的消息依然接踵而至
And yet news of calamity does not end with their deaths.
群龙无首  恐怕科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯的人马
Absent proper command, I fear Cossinius and Furius' men
很快就会一溃而散
will soon be scattered to the winds.
我还没到  他们的将军就毙命了  真不幸
Yes it was most unfortunate their leaders fell before my arrival.
更不幸的是  你派出去的信使
Even more unfortunate that your messenger appears
所走的路线太靠近叛军营地了
to have taken routes that passed so near the rebel encampment.
有话直说
Give plain voice.
如果你同意的话
If you're of a mind.
我们不要纠结于过去  而要着眼于未来
Let us move from clouded past and turn eye towards pressing future.
剿灭斯巴达克斯的大任
Sole command and charge to bring Spartacus
全仰仗你了
to deserved end is now yours.
如果你希望的话  还有大将军的头衔
Along with title of Imperator, if you so wish it.
我为罗马的荣耀而战
I serve the glory of Rome.
我们都一样
As do we all.
原来是您计划好的
You planned this.
就在他提出您听命于科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯时
From the moment Metellus offered command under Cossinius and Furius.
克拉苏家族绝不向他人卑躬屈膝
The House of Crassus bows to no one.
您怎么知道斯巴达克斯会取他们的性命
How did you know Spartacus would make attempt on their lives,
而不是在得知您从罗马出兵时
instead of fleeing when knowledge was gained
四散而逃呢
of your army advancing from Rome?
因为换作我  我也会如此
Because it is what I would have done.
莫姆缪斯和罗马残兵往西边逃跑了
Mummius and the last of the Romans flee to the west.
看到木桩上插着将军的脑袋  他们吓破了胆
Sight of their leader's heads upon pike has broken fucking spirit.
那我们乘胜追击  把他们一举歼灭
Let us give chase, and see them all to equal fate.
我们已经打赢了
We have won our victory.
我们要赶在克拉苏的军队到来之前远离此地
I would see us far from here in advance of Crassus and his army.
无敌的斯巴达克斯也有打不过逃跑的时候
The mighty Spartacus turns from unwinnable fight?
我们的人数增长之快  远远超过预料
Our numbers have grown beyond wildest expectation.
问题是凛冬将至
Yet winter will soon be upon us.
既要对付克拉苏  又要对抗饥饿和寒冷
To face hunger and cold as well as Crassus
那我们必死无疑
would drag us to certain doom.
我们必须找到有补给能过冬的地方
We must seek advantage of supplies and shelter.
还要易守难攻
One that can be defended if set upon,
等开春再举大业
until spring warms intent.
没有哪座宅子能容纳这么多人
There is not a villa in all the lands that could hold so many.
的确没有
No, there is not.
要有一座城才能容纳我们
Only a city could hold us now.
我们要从罗马身上撕一块肉下来
And we shall tear one from the flesh of Rome,
用鲜血和死亡
and salt mortal wound
给他们的伤口撒一把盐
with With blood and death.